Guide to the Edward Carter Papers ALBA.228
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Edward Carter Papers
1941-2001
1942-1999
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Carter, Allene G.
Carter, Edward A., -1963
ALBA.228
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Edward Allen Carter, II (1916-1963) was raised in Shanghai, China. In 1937, he joined the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and fought in the Spanish Civil War. During World War II, Carter distinguished himself in battle in Germany, but his service went unrecognized by the Army due to discrimination against African Americans. More than three decades after his death, the Army and the U.S. government finally honored Carter's bravery in action. This collection primarily consists of documents related to Carter's experiences in the U.S. Army.
Historical/Biographical Note
Edward Allen Carter, II (1916-1963) was born in Los Angeles to missionary parents, and raised in Shanghai, China. As a teenager he joined the Chinese Nationalist Army to fight the Japanese, winning rapid advancement. He later joined the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and served in Spain, beginning in June 1937. Carter enlisted in the U.S. Army in September 1941 and was shipped overseas in November 1944. In 1945, while stationed in Germany, Carter distinguished himself in battle, suffering multiple bullet wounds. His heroic actions went unheralded by the U.S. Army for many years, due largely to discrimination against African Americans. Suspicion of Carter's political background led the Army to reject his effort to re-enlist in 1949. Carter died on January 30, 1963. More than three decades after his death, the Army and the U.S. government finally recognized Carter's bravery with a Congress Medal of Honor. The U.S. also named a ship after Carter, and his body was re-interred at Arlington National Cemetery in 1997.
Provenance
The bulk of the Edward Carter Papers were donated to New York University in 2005 by Allene G. Carter, Edward Carter's daughter-in-law. One set of the Freedom of Information Act papers were acquired in 2005, and donated to New York University by Michael Nash.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Separated Materials
Photographs from the Edward Carter Collection have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Arrangement
The files are arranged in alphabetical order.
The collection is organized into one series:
Missing Title
Series I: General
The files are arranged in alphabetical order.
Scope and Content Note
This collection primarily consists of photocopied documents related to Carter's experiences in the U.S. Army. All the papers post-date Carter's involvement in the Spanish Civil War. Materials include clippings pertaining to Carter's World War II service; letters from Carter to his wife, Mildred Hoover Carter, written while in service with the U.S. Army; and flyers for the Negro American Labor Council and the March on Washington. Also includes a report on Army discrimination against African Americans; a letter and citation signed by President Bill Clinton and documents associated with the ceremony for an Army supply ship named after Carter; and biographical materials outlining Carter's heroic service in World War II. Photographs include Carter in uniform, photos related to the presentation of his Congress Medal of Honor; his reburial at Arlington Cemetery in 1997; the ship naming ceremony; and a photo of Allene G. Carter with Bill Clinton. Also included are minutes and photographs, probably belonged to by Jesse Vaughn, Allene Carter's father, relating to the United Packinghouse Workers of America.
Articles.; Correspondence.; World War, 1939-1945 |x Campaigns |z Germany.; World War, 1939-1945 |x Medals |z United States.; World War, 1939-1945 -- African Americans.; African American soldiers |v Biography.; Carter, Allene G.; Carter, Mildred Hoover; United Packinghouse, Food, and Allied Workers
- General
  - Clippings (photocopies), Undated, 1945-1946, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Congress Medal of Honor: Ceremony photographs, citations, correspondence (photocopies), 1997, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Adjutant General to Mildred Carter (photocopy), 1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Edward Carter to Mildred Carter (photocopies), 1941, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Flyers: Negro American Labor Council; March on Washington (photocopies), 1960, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Freedom of Information Act: Declassified documents, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Freedom of Information Act: FBI Files (Set 1), 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Freedom of Information Act: FBI Files (Set 2), 1942-1943, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Honoring Sergeant Carter: Book promotion, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - M/V SSG Edward A. Carter Jr. (T-AK 4544): U.S. Navy ship naming ceremony, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Report on incidents of racial discrimination in U.S. Army, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Union minutes and photographs (photocopies), Undated, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - World War II: Official documents (photocopies), 1941, 1945, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - World War II: Photographs (photocopies), circa 1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)